<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Simon Gravelle</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/</link><atom:link href="https://simongravelle.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Simon Gravelle</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://simongravelle.github.io/media/logo_hu5025324560545862583.png</url><title>Simon Gravelle</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/</link></image><item><title>Running for the CNRS National Committee – Section 08</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2025-conrs.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2025-conrs.html</guid><description>&lt;p>I am running as a candidate for the &lt;em>Collège B1&lt;/em> of the new Section 08 of the CoNRS:&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Physique de la matière complexe et du vivant&lt;/strong> (Physics of Complex Matter and Life).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Personal statement (See French version here below)&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recruited at LIPhy in 2023 by the former Section 11, I study soft matter systems
(polymers, bio-inspired systems, nanoporous materials), with a focus on the
behavior of molecules at interfaces. I primarily use molecular simulation, and my
background, which combines simulations and experiments, facilitates my
collaborations with experimentalists (NMR, neutrons, X-rays). I also dedicate time
to creating open and freely accessible educational content for both beginners and
experts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The CNRS remains one of the few institutions that guarantees independent research
that is not subject to trends—an essential condition for producing critical, open,
and long-term knowledge. In this regard, the National Committee plays a
fundamental role as a space for scientific collegiality, debate, and counterbalance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As an elected member, I am committed to fully dedicating myself to the National
Committee and to contributing to recruitment and evaluation processes in a
thoughtful way, not based solely on bibliometric indicators. I will work to equally
defend interdisciplinarity, established disciplines, and emerging themes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Profession de foi (In French)&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recruté au LIPhy en 2023 par l’ancienne Section 11, j’étudie les systèmes de la
matière molle (polymères, systèmes bio-inspirés, matériaux nanoporeux), avec un
intérêt pour le comportement des molécules aux interfaces. J’utilise principalement
la simulation moléculaire, et mon parcours mêlant simulations et expériences facilite
mes collaborations avec les expérimentateurs (RMN, neutrons,
rayons X). Je consacre aussi du temps à la création de contenus pédagogiques
libres et ouverts pour débutants et experts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Le CNRS reste l’un des rares organismes à garantir une recherche indépendante et
non soumise aux effets de mode, conditions indispensables à la production de
savoirs critiques, ouverts et de long terme. À ce titre, le Comité National joue un rôle fondamental
en tant qu’espace de collégialité scientifique, de débat et de contre-pouvoir.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>En tant que membre élu, je m’engage à me consacrer pleinement au Comité National
et à contribuer aux recrutements et aux évaluations de façon raisonnée et non
fondée uniquement sur des indicateurs bibliométriques, afin de défendre de manière égale
l’interdisciplinarité, les disciplines reconnues et les thématiques émergentes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>I am migrating to the Fediverse</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2025-mastodon.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2025-mastodon.html</guid><description>&lt;p>Starting now, I am migrating to the Fediverse and
will no longer be publishing on X. This also applies to the communication
associated with the LAMMPS Tutorials organization.
The main exceptions are my LinkedIn and Youtube accounts that I am keeping (for now).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Fediverse is a network of social
platforms. Its decentralized nature prevents corporate monopolies and censorship.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can follow me on Mastodon (&lt;a href="https://mastodon.social/@simongravelle%29" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://mastodon.social/@simongravelle)&lt;/a>, where
I will primarily post about science, molecular simulations, and open-source projects.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>New ANR project - CO₂ capture by foam</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2025-anr-miamco2.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2025-anr-miamco2.html</guid><description>&lt;p>This marks the official start of an ANR project led by Elise Lorenceau, in collaboration
with the CEA. Together, we aim to demonstrate the feasibility of a foam reactor
for CO₂ capture.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title/><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/gallery/systems.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/gallery/systems.html</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="systems-that-interest-me">Systems that interest me&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Soft matter systems, such as polymers and proteins&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fluids in confined environments or near interfaces&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title/><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/gallery/methods.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/gallery/methods.html</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="preferred-method">Preferred method&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Molecular simulations, particulalry when it can be compared to experiments like neutrons or NMR.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Set of Tutorials for the LAMMPS Simulation Package</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2025_gravelle_arxiv_a_set_of.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2025_gravelle_arxiv_a_set_of.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Adsorption Selectivity of Water-Ethanol Mixtures on Organosilica Surfaces: Role of Hydrophilicity</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2025_gravelle_hal_adsorption_selectivity_of.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2025_gravelle_hal_adsorption_selectivity_of.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Effect of thermal fluctuations on the average shape of a graphene nanosheet suspended in a shear flow</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2025_gravelle_acta_mechanica_effect_of_thermal.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2025_gravelle_acta_mechanica_effect_of_thermal.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Exploring the Impact of Minor Water Content on Polymer Electrolytes with Molecular Dynamics</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2025_asha_the_journal_of_physical_chemistry_b_exploring_the_impact.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2025_asha_the_journal_of_physical_chemistry_b_exploring_the_impact.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Giant mobility of surface-trapped ionic charges following liquid tribocharging</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2025_benrahla_arxiv_giant_mobility_of.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2025_benrahla_arxiv_giant_mobility_of.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Intermittent molecular motion and first passage statistics for the NMR relaxation of confined water</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2025_gravelle_arxiv_intermittent_molecular_motion.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2025_gravelle_arxiv_intermittent_molecular_motion.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Focus on Learn Molecular Simulation with Python</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2024-mdcourse.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2024-mdcourse.html</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://mdcourse.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Learn Molecular Simulations with Python&lt;/a>
is designed as a step-by-step guide to developing simple Python code that
includes the basic functionalities of molecular dynamics and Monte Carlo
simulations. The main goal is to help users understand the fundamentals of
molecular simulation algorithms. The scripts will also be used for small
scientific projects. In particular, some of the earliest results obtained
from molecular simulations, including the pioneering works by Metropolis,
Rosenbluth, Wood, and Parker in the 1950s, will be re-explored.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you want to take part in the project, reach out to me on
&lt;a href="https://github.com/mdcourse" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub&lt;/a>. I am looking for contributors
(co-writers, testers).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This project has received funding from the European Union&amp;rsquo;s Horizon 2020
research and innovation programme under the Marie Skłodowska-Curie grant
agreement No 101065060.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>PostDoc Position Available in LIPhy (Filled)</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2024-postdoc-offer.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2024-postdoc-offer.html</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Scope.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Polymers are versatile, durable, and cost-effective materials essential in packaging, construction, and electronics. Polymers of Intrinsic Microporosity (PIMs) represent a special class with rigid ring-shaped molecules forming interconnected voids of 0.2 to 2 nanometers. PIMs have high specific surface areas and are scalable, making them ideal for gas adsorption and mixture separation. However, only a few fluid mixtures can currently be separated using nanoporous materials, with most methods still relying on costly thermal processes such as distillation. Developing new nanopore-based separation processes could address environmental issues such as water contamination and CO2 emissions. To facilitate the emergence of these new processes, a better understanding of the complex behaviors of nanoconfined fluid mixtures is crucial. Achieving this goal requires novel multiscale approaches to connect the molecular details of confined molecules at the nanoscale to macroscopic transport properties. The aim of this postdoctoral position is to correlate the molecular properties of fluid mixtures in a microporous polymer with its large-scale permeability and selectivity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Activities&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Development of realistic models of mixtures in microporous polymers using molecular simulations.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Characterization of the structural and dynamic properties of confined fluids and their interactions with polymer surfaces.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Upscaling of molecular results to the macroscopic scale using a lattice-based approach.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Utilization of the lattice model to predict the macroscopic permeability and selectivity of PIM membranes.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Skills&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The postdoctoral candidate must hold a PhD in physics, statistical mechanics, physical chemistry, or materials science, and have some experience in scientific programming and molecular simulations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Work Context&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>LIPhy is an interdisciplinary physics laboratory that brings together experts in the theory and experimentation of soft matter systems and fluids at interfaces. Located in Grenoble, LIPhy is surrounded by physics, chemistry, and biology laboratories, offering potential collaboration opportunities with experimental groups (SAXS, SANS, etc.) based on the candidate&amp;rsquo;s interests.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The position is located in a sector under the protection of scientific and technical potential (PPST), and therefore requires, in accordance with the regulations, that your arrival is authorized by the competent authority of the MESR.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Starting date&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>February 2025, or after.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Apply.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Candicates can apply from the &lt;a href="https://emploi.cnrs.fr/Offres/CDD/UMR5588-SIMGRA-001/Default.aspx?lang=EN" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CNRS website&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>In silico design and prediction of metastable quaternary phases in Cu–Ni–Si–Cr alloys</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2024_2_4_carral_apl_machine_learning_in_silico_design.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2024_2_4_carral_apl_machine_learning_in_silico_design.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Probing atomic-scale processes at the ferrihydrite-water interface with reactive molecular dynamics</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2024_25_1_hayatifar_geochemical_transactions_probing_atomic-scale_processes.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2024_25_1_hayatifar_geochemical_transactions_probing_atomic-scale_processes.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>PhD Position Available in LIPhy (Filled)</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2023-phd-offer.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2023-phd-offer.html</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Update.&lt;/strong> The offer has now expired, and the selection process has moved to the next step.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Scope.&lt;/strong> With the goal to reach carbon neutrality by 2050, direct air capture (DAC) of CO2 from wet flue
gases is one brick of the carbon mitigation strategy – especially with the next generation of solid porous
sorbents based on Metal-Organic Frameworks (MOF). While thermodynamics of the CO2 capture is well
documented in the literature, little is known about molecular diffusion and transport properties in MOF
angstropores (in particular, in the presence of environmental humidity). Also, diffusion through pore scales
of the applicative sorbing medium, ranging from nanopores (pore diameter ~nm) to macropores (&amp;gt; 50 nm)
and beyond remain open. In order to fill the gap and gain insight into multiscale transport properties and
try to figure CO2 capture optimization through MOF based sorbents, we ambition to develop a multiscale
approach based on a lattice model fed by molecular simulations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In more detail, the objective of this PhD proposal is two-fold. i. Using molecular simulations [e.g. Magnin
et al. J. Phys. Chem. C 2022], we aim to unravel the molecular phenomena that govern the thermodynamic
and kinetic mechanisms when capturing CO2 using a multi-scale porous material. With this first aspect,
we aim to rationalize the use of nanoporous materials for practical engineering processes by developing
a robust and general methodology to link physico-chemical properties at different scales. ii. Using a
bottom-up strategy, we will upscale the results obtained using atomistic simulations to mimic phase
separation and transport of CO2/N2/H2O mixtures at the macroscale. To do so, a simple yet realistic lattice
model [Botan et al. Phys. Rev. E 2015], which can be seen as a pore network model accounting for the
change of the local thermodynamic/transport properties in a kinetic engineering process (e.g. Pressure
Swing Adsorption), will be used.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Potential candidate.&lt;/strong> The PhD candidate should have a background in physics, physical
chemistry/chemical physics or materials science. He/she should also have some experience in scientific
programming and a background in statistical mechanics (including if possible Monte Carlo or/and
Molecular Dynamics).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Practical aspects.&lt;/strong> The position is available starting January 2024 and lasts for 36 months. The PhD student
will work under the supervision of Benoit Coasne/Simon Gravelle (LIPhy, Grenoble) and Yann Magnin
(CSTJF, Pau). He/she will be located at LIPhy in Grenoble, France but several short stays in CSTJF in
Pau, France will be planned. Applicants should provide a CV, a letter of motivation and the names and
email addresses of 2 or 3 references to:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Yann Magnin (yann.magnin at totalenergies.com)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Benoit Coasne (benoit.coasne at univ-grenoble-alpes.fr)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Simon Gravelle (simon.gravelle at univ-grenoble-alpes.fr)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>More information:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://benoitcoasne.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://benoitcoasne.github.io/&lt;/a> (Coasne’s research group website)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.yann-magnin.fr/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.yann-magnin.fr/&lt;/a> (research website)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>I have obtained a position at French CNRS</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2023-cnrs-start.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2023-cnrs-start.html</guid><description>&lt;p>In the continuity of my MSCA fellowship, I&amp;rsquo;ve been hired by the French CNRS (Section 11) as a tenured full time researcher at &lt;a href="https://liphy.univ-grenoble-alpes.fr/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LIPhy&lt;/a> (UGA).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The version 2.0 of LAMMPS tutorials has been released</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2023-lammpstutorial-v2.0.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2023-lammpstutorial-v2.0.html</guid><description>&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://lammpstutorials.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">version 2.0&lt;/a> of LAMMPS tutorial has just been published, and offers:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>a new structure with a sphinx template&lt;/li>
&lt;li>tutorials are now written in rst format, instead of html, which should facilitate future collaborations&lt;/li>
&lt;li>a gorgeous dark mode (for the tutorials, not yet for the index page)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://lammpstutorials.github.io/lammpstutorials-version1.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">version 1.0&lt;/a> is still visible here, but is not maintained and some commands are likely to be obsolete.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Assessing the validity of NMR relaxation rates obtained from coarse-grained simulations of PEG–water mixtures</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2023_127_25_gravelle_the_journal_of_physical_chemistry_b_assessing_the_validity.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2023_127_25_gravelle_the_journal_of_physical_chemistry_b_assessing_the_validity.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>NMR Investigation of Water in Salt Crusts: Insights from Experiments and Molecular Simulations</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2023_39_22_gravelle_langmuir_nmr_investigation_of.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2023_39_22_gravelle_langmuir_nmr_investigation_of.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Stability of binary precipitates in Cu-Ni-Si-Cr alloys investigated through active learning</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2023_306_carral_materials_chemistry_and_physics_stability_of_binary.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2023_306_carral_materials_chemistry_and_physics_stability_of_binary.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Use of nanoporous carbon membranes for separating aqueous/organic mixtures</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2023_bocquet_patent_use_of_nanoporous.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2023_bocquet_patent_use_of_nanoporous.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Transport of thin water films: From thermally activated random walks to hydrodynamics</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2022_157_10_gravelle_the_journal_of_chemical_physics_transport_of_thin.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2022_157_10_gravelle_the_journal_of_chemical_physics_transport_of_thin.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Viscous peeling of a nanosheet</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2022_18_20_agrawal_soft_matter_viscous_peeling_of.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2022_18_20_agrawal_soft_matter_viscous_peeling_of.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Adsorption of single and multiple graphene-oxide nanoparticles at a water–vapor interface</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2021_37_45_gravelle_langmuir_adsorption_of_single.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2021_37_45_gravelle_langmuir_adsorption_of_single.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Alignment of a flexible platelike particle in shear flow: Effect of surface slip and edges</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2021_6_8_kamal_physical_review_fluids_alignment_of_a.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2021_6_8_kamal_physical_review_fluids_alignment_of_a.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Effect of hydrodynamic slip on the rotational dynamics of a thin Brownian platelet in shear flow</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2021_919_kamal_journal_of_fluid_mechanics_effect_of_hydrodynamic.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2021_919_kamal_journal_of_fluid_mechanics_effect_of_hydrodynamic.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Violations of Jeffery's theory in the dynamics of nanographene in shear flow</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2021_6_3_gravelle_physical_review_fluids_violations_of_jefferys.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2021_6_3_gravelle_physical_review_fluids_violations_of_jefferys.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>A multi-scale model for fluid transport through a bio-inspired passive valve</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2020_152_1_gravelle_the_journal_of_chemical_physics_a_multi-scale_model.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2020_152_1_gravelle_the_journal_of_chemical_physics_a_multi-scale_model.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Design of a unidirectional water valve in Tillandsia</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2020_11_1_raux_nature_communications_design_of_a.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2020_11_1_raux_nature_communications_design_of_a.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Hydrodynamic slip can align thin nanoplatelets in shear flow</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2020_11_1_kamal_nature_communications_hydrodynamic_slip_can.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2020_11_1_kamal_nature_communications_hydrodynamic_slip_can.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Liquid exfoliation of multilayer graphene in sheared solvents: A molecular dynamics investigation</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2020_152_10_gravelle_the_journal_of_chemical_physics_liquid_exfoliation_of.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2020_152_10_gravelle_the_journal_of_chemical_physics_liquid_exfoliation_of.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Adsorption kinetics in open nanopores as a source of low-frequency noise</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2019_19_10_gravelle_nano_letters_adsorption_kinetics_in.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2019_19_10_gravelle_nano_letters_adsorption_kinetics_in.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Flow-induced shift of the Donnan equilibrium for ultra-sensitive mass transport measurement through a single nanochannel</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2019_151_24_gravelle_the_journal_of_chemical_physics_flow-induced_shift_of.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2019_151_24_gravelle_the_journal_of_chemical_physics_flow-induced_shift_of.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Anomalous capillary filling and wettability reversal in nanochannels</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2016_93_3_gravelle_physical_review_e_anomalous_capillary_filling.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2016_93_3_gravelle_physical_review_e_anomalous_capillary_filling.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Carbon membranes for efficient water-ethanol separation</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2016_145_12_gravelle_the_journal_of_chemical_physics_carbon_membranes_for.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2016_145_12_gravelle_the_journal_of_chemical_physics_carbon_membranes_for.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Forces behind plant cell division</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2016_113_32_guerin_proceedings_of_the_national_academy_of_sciences_forces_behind_plant.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2016_113_32_guerin_proceedings_of_the_national_academy_of_sciences_forces_behind_plant.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Nanofluidics: a pedagogical introduction</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2016_gravelle_hal_nanofluidics_a_pedagogical.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2016_gravelle_hal_nanofluidics_a_pedagogical.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Nanofluidics: a theoretical and numerical investigation of fluid transport in nanochannels</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2015_gravelle_these_nanofluidics_a_theoretical.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2015_gravelle_these_nanofluidics_a_theoretical.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Perméabilité optimale des aquaporines : une histoire de forme ?</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2015_31_2_gravelle_med_sci_permeabilite_optimale_des.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2015_31_2_gravelle_med_sci_permeabilite_optimale_des.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Large permeabilities of hourglass nanopores: From hydrodynamics to single file transport</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2014_141_18_gravelle_the_journal_of_chemical_physics_large_permeabilities_of.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2014_141_18_gravelle_the_journal_of_chemical_physics_large_permeabilities_of.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Sub-additive ionic transport across arrays of solid-state nanopores</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2014_26_1_gadaleta_physics_of_fluids_sub-additive_ionic_transport.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2014_26_1_gadaleta_physics_of_fluids_sub-additive_ionic_transport.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Nanofluidic osmotic diodes: Theory and molecular dynamics simulations</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2013_111_24_picallo_physical_review_letters_nanofluidic_osmotic_diodes.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2013_111_24_picallo_physical_review_letters_nanofluidic_osmotic_diodes.html</guid><description/></item><item><title>Optimizing water permeability through the hourglass shape of aquaporins</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2013_110_41_gravelle_proceedings_of_the_national_academy_of_sciences_optimizing_water_permeability.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/publications/2013_110_41_gravelle_proceedings_of_the_national_academy_of_sciences_optimizing_water_permeability.html</guid><description/></item><item><title/><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/admin.yml</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/admin.yml</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>