<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Personal | Simon Gravelle</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/tag/personal.html</link><atom:link href="https://simongravelle.github.io/tag/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Personal</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://simongravelle.github.io/media/logo_hu5025324560545862583.png</url><title>Personal</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/tag/personal.html</link></image><item><title>Running for the CNRS National Committee – Section 08</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2025-conrs.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2025-conrs.html</guid><description>&lt;p>I am running as a candidate for the &lt;em>Collège B1&lt;/em> of the new Section 08 of the CoNRS:&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Physique de la matière complexe et du vivant&lt;/strong> (Physics of Complex Matter and Life).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Personal statement (See French version here below)&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recruited at LIPhy in 2023 by the former Section 11, I study soft matter systems
(polymers, bio-inspired systems, nanoporous materials), with a focus on the
behavior of molecules at interfaces. I primarily use molecular simulation, and my
background, which combines simulations and experiments, facilitates my
collaborations with experimentalists (NMR, neutrons, X-rays). I also dedicate time
to creating open and freely accessible educational content for both beginners and
experts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The CNRS remains one of the few institutions that guarantees independent research
that is not subject to trends—an essential condition for producing critical, open,
and long-term knowledge. In this regard, the National Committee plays a
fundamental role as a space for scientific collegiality, debate, and counterbalance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As an elected member, I am committed to fully dedicating myself to the National
Committee and to contributing to recruitment and evaluation processes in a
thoughtful way, not based solely on bibliometric indicators. I will work to equally
defend interdisciplinarity, established disciplines, and emerging themes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Profession de foi (In French)&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recruté au LIPhy en 2023 par l’ancienne Section 11, j’étudie les systèmes de la
matière molle (polymères, systèmes bio-inspirés, matériaux nanoporeux), avec un
intérêt pour le comportement des molécules aux interfaces. J’utilise principalement
la simulation moléculaire, et mon parcours mêlant simulations et expériences facilite
mes collaborations avec les expérimentateurs (RMN, neutrons,
rayons X). Je consacre aussi du temps à la création de contenus pédagogiques
libres et ouverts pour débutants et experts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Le CNRS reste l’un des rares organismes à garantir une recherche indépendante et
non soumise aux effets de mode, conditions indispensables à la production de
savoirs critiques, ouverts et de long terme. À ce titre, le Comité National joue un rôle fondamental
en tant qu’espace de collégialité scientifique, de débat et de contre-pouvoir.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>En tant que membre élu, je m’engage à me consacrer pleinement au Comité National
et à contribuer aux recrutements et aux évaluations de façon raisonnée et non
fondée uniquement sur des indicateurs bibliométriques, afin de défendre de manière égale
l’interdisciplinarité, les disciplines reconnues et les thématiques émergentes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sasha (Aleksandra) Ardaševa</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/group/sasha.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/group/sasha.html</guid><description>&lt;p>Research associate on the MIAM-CO2 project since May 2025.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>I am migrating to the Fediverse</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2025-mastodon.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2025-mastodon.html</guid><description>&lt;p>Starting now, I am migrating to the Fediverse and
will no longer be publishing on X. This also applies to the communication
associated with the LAMMPS Tutorials organization.
The main exceptions are my LinkedIn and Youtube accounts that I am keeping (for now).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Fediverse is a network of social
platforms. Its decentralized nature prevents corporate monopolies and censorship.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can follow me on Mastodon (&lt;a href="https://mastodon.social/@simongravelle%29" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://mastodon.social/@simongravelle)&lt;/a>, where
I will primarily post about science, molecular simulations, and open-source projects.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>New ANR project - CO₂ capture by foam</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2025-anr-miamco2.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/news/2025-anr-miamco2.html</guid><description>&lt;p>This marks the official start of an ANR project led by Elise Lorenceau, in collaboration
with the CEA. Together, we aim to demonstrate the feasibility of a foam reactor
for CO₂ capture.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Pablo Grisanti</title><link>https://simongravelle.github.io/group/pablo.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simongravelle.github.io/group/pablo.html</guid><description>&lt;p>PhD candidate at LIPhy, Université Grenoble Alpes, since April 2024.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>